Guide to the Harris Pierce Photographs 1888-1900 PR 270
New-York Historical Society
Harris Pierce photographs
1888-1900
New-York Historical Society
Pierce, Harris
PR 270
5.5 Linear feet
Photographs of street gradings and improvements, as well as residences and businesses in the Bronx during the mid 1890s. Digital copies of the images in the collection are available on-line through the Digital Collections pages of N-YHS's website.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Herbert Berger-Hershkowitz, 6 July 2007.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Biographical Note
Little is known about Harris Pierce, but his stamp appears on the verso of the photographs, and gives his address as 1921 Oostdorp Ave and his profession as 'Photographer'. Oostdorp St. is the former name of the present Bryant Avenue from East Tremont Avenue to Bronx Park. 1921 Oostdorp Avenue was on the west side, south of E 177th Street and north of Boston Road. Trow's New York City Directory lists Harris Pierce's profession from 1883-1908 as 'Stenographer' at various addresses on Nassau Street, with his home in the West Farms area of the Bronx.
The photographs appear to have been made as evidence in supporting the cases of claimants filing for damages against the city. Some of the photographs are mounted on boards with a form on the verso for recording information about the image. The form includes the names of Thomas S. Bassford and Ernest Hall, lawyers representing the claimants.
Scope and Content Note
The Harris Pierce photographs span the period from 1888-1900 and primarily include 300 gelatin silver photographs of residences and businesses during the grading and improvements of streets in the Bronx. The photographs include views of the construction of sewers, construction sites, street improvements and grading, residences, vegetable gardens, children, churches, and businesses such as grocery stores, brewers and liquor stores, bakers, barbers, plumbers, and real estate offices. The photographs also include views of the New York Central Harlem Line and train stations such as the Tremont Station, social clubs such as the Suburban Club, the Artistic Bronze Co., the American Pie Baking Co., and stables and feed stores.
Most of the photographs are marked on the verso with either the street address or the block and lot numbers. The majority of the photographs were made along Webster Avenue, Vanderbilt (now Park) Avenue, Brooke Avenue, and Washington Avenue from 144th Street in the south to 178th Street in the north. Many of the photographs were made along Vanderbilt Avenue, which from E 161 St to 167 St was the 19th century name for the present Park Avenue. Below 161 Street the avenue was referred to as Railroad Avenue, or RR Avenue. The photographs marked with either street addresses or intersections in brackets were given based on the block and lot numbers. These addresses were derived by consulting the 1897 Atlas of the City of New York: 23rd & 24th Wards from Actual Surveys and Official Plans by George W. and Walter S. Bromley.
The block numbers given on the photographs are numbers from prior to the annexation of 1895, including those photographs that are dated after that year. In 1874 the city of New York annexed the area of the Bronx south of Yonkers and west of the Bronx River from Westchester County. This area was given block and lot numbers that were used until the 1895 annexation of the Bronx east of the Bronx River. After 1895 the numbering system for blocks was changed. The new (post-1895) block numbers can be found on maps after 1895 with the 'old' numbers marked in parentheses. It appears that the photographer was using the term 'ward number' for what was actually the lot number. All the photographs were made in the twenty-third and twenty-fourth wards (the Bronx).
Photographs that could not be identified based on the geographic location of the subject were placed into the "Unidentified" folders and further divided by type of building: commercial, empty lots, and residences. These photographs include many of the same subjects as the identified photographs, but lack both block and lot numbers and street addresses.
The only photograph in the collection that is known not to have been made by Harris Pierce is the view of 1940 Park Avenue taken by Louis C. Bennett.
Arrangement
Arranged by street name, then unidentified photographs by building type.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
For other materials relating to the Bronx see the Geographic File (PR 020), and for transportation in the Bronx see the Subway Construction Photograph Collection (PR 069).
On-line Digital Collection
Digital copies of the images in the collection were made by N-YHS and are available on-line through the Digital Collections pages of N-YHS's website.
Other Finding Aids
A detailed spreadsheet listing all the photographs in the collection with property owner, address, block and lot number, date, and building type can be found in the collection file in the Print Room.
Buildings -- New York (State) -- Bronx County.; Dwellings -- New York (State) -- Bronx County.; Grading (Earthwork) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Pavements -- New York (State) -- New York.; Roads -- Design and construction -- New York (State) -- New York.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York -- Maintenance and repair.; Gelatin silver prints.; Photographic prints.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Bassford, Thomas S., 1861-1921; Hall, Ernest, 1845-1920
- Brook Avenue, 1896-98 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Courtlandt Avenue, 1894-95 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Olin Avenue, 1896-98 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Park Avenue, 1898 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Railroad Avenue, 1893-94 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Spencer Place, 1896 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Talmadge Street, 1896 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Tremont Ave, n. d. (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Vanderbilt Avenue, 1891, 1894-98 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12-25)
- Washington Avenue, 1891, 1894-95 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26-29)
- Webster Avenue, 1896-97 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
- Williamsbridge, 1897 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
- 144th Street, 1891, 1893, 1895 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
- 146th Street, 1893 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
- 148th Street, 1891, 1893-94 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
- 149th Street, 1891, 1894 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
- 150th-151st Streets, 1891 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
- 155th Street, 1893 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
- 156th Street, 1896, 1898 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
- 160-161st Street, 1891, 1894, 1896 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
- 162nd Street, 1894 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
- 163rd Street, 1891, 1894-96 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 41-43)
- 167th Street, 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 44)
- 173th Street, 1894, 1896 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 46)
- 174th Street, 1896 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 47)
- 175th Street, 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 48)
- 176th Street, 1896 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 49)
- 177th Street, 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 50)
- 178th Street, 1894-95 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 51)
- 183rd Street, 1894 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 52)
- Unidentified -- Commercial, 1888, 1896-98 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 53)
- Unidentified -- Empty Lots, 1896-98 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 54-55)
- Unidentified -- Residential, 1893, 1896-98, 1900 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 56-62)